Guide to the Anson Conger Goodyear Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- POLITICAL ASSOCIATES OF LINCOLN
  - Henry J. Raymond, journalist. A.L.S. 6pp. 8mo, New York, August 11, 1864. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    From the contents it is supposed that this letter was written to W.P. Fessenden. It discusses the coming campaign and says that Lincoln's election will be very difficult. It mentions the necessity for raising money and his having approached government contractors for contributions. Raymond was editor of the New York Times and also speaker of the New York Assembly in 1861.
  - Gideon Welles, A.L.S. 4pp. 8mo., Hartford, November 21, 1873 to Ira Harris. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Strongly criticizing Seward and his endeavors to create the impression that Lincoln was dominated by him.
  - Horatio Seymour, Governor of New York, proclamation 2pp. 4to., Executive Chamber, Albany, May 10, 1864. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Announcing the death of General James S. Wadsworth and ordering flags displayed at half mast on the Capitol and on all arsenals of the State.
  - John Sherman, A.L.S. 4pp. 8mo., November 1, 1862, to Schuyler Colfax. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Reviewing the results of two years of the War. Speaks of his discouragement at the President's want of energy, etc.
  - Charles Sumner, A.L.S. 3pp., February 7, 1863. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Referring to interviews with Lincoln; at the end of the 3rd p. is a note in pencil signed "H.W.B."
  - James Garfield, A.L.S., September 15, 1864, 3pp. 4to. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Horace Greeley, A.L.S., April 17, 1848, 2pp. 4to. (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Hatch, [I? or J?]T., A.L.S., Buffalo, March 10, 1863. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- ABRAHAM LINCOLN NORTH AND SOUTH
  - General Isaac Stevens, A.L.S. 4pp. 4to, Beaufort, South Carolina, April 23, 1862, to W.P. Fessenden. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Speaking enthusiastically of his impression of Lincoln at his first interview and his devotion to Lincoln.
  - John Bright, English Statesman, A.L.S. 4pp. 8mo. Rochdale, October 1, 1864, to Horace Greeley. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Giving his observations on the feelings of Englishmen in relation to the re-election of Lincoln and the Rebellion. Praises the President and criticizes McClellan.
  - Richard H. Stoddard, A.L. signed with initials, 2pp. 8mo. New York, May 2, 1865. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Referring to his ode on the death of Lincoln with copy in pencil signed of this ode as it was submitted for publication dated Christmas 1877. Also note partly in ink and partly in pencil addressed to Golder regarding the Lincoln ode.
  - James Whitcomb Riley, A.L.S. 1p. 8mo. Indianapolis, June 24, 1890, to Robert Underwood Johnson. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Referring to Lincoln and Riley's poems.
  - Horace Greeley, A.L.S. 1p. 8mo., Office of the Tribune, New York, July 24, 1867, to E.A. Stansbury. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Referring to Lincoln and implying that the Emancipation was due to Greeley although Lincoln got the credit for it.
  - Sumner, Charles, A.L.S. to Gideon Welles. Cotuit, [Mass.], July 5, 1865. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Mary Lincoln, A.L.S. 4pp., crossed. Frankfurt, A.M., April 3, 1874, to Mrs. Orne. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Speaking of her husband's services to his country, bitterly criticizing Grant, her own sickness, etc.
  - General Edward S. Bragg, A.L.S. 2pp. 4to, Washington, May 5, 1860. Written to his wife. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    Describing the Democratic convention, which had just closed without being able to agree upon a candidate.
  - To Whom it May Concern - a forgery. (Box 2, Folder 7)
- JEFFERSON DAVIS AND GENERAL P.G.T. BEAUREGARD
  - W. Porcher Miles, A.L.S., 4pp. 8vo, August 1, 1861. Addressed to General Beauregard. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Referring to Miles' application to Jefferson Davis for supplies and transportation for Beauregard's army. Miles was a member of the Confederate Congress.
  - Jefferson Davis
    - A.L.S., 3pp. 4to, August 4, 1861. To General Beauregard. (Box 2, Folder 8)
      In reference to the same suggestion. With copy of letter from Beauregard to Davis dated August 10, 1861, replying to Davis' letter.
    - A.L.S., 3pp. 8vo., October 30, 1861. To General Beauregard. (Box 2, Folder 8)
      The celebrated letter in which Davis accuses Beauregard of trying to exalt himself at Davis' expense, as Beauregard had asserted that Davis had prevented him from moving on and capturing Washington. With notes on the back in hand of General Jordan.
    - A.L.S., 1p. 8vo., November 9, 1861. (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Asking for copies of his letters to Beauregard.
    - A.L.S., 2pp. 8vo., April 1, 1878. (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Thanking Beauregard for his offer to loan Davis his papers relating to the War.
    - A.L.S., 8pp. 4to, September 25, 1879. (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Of great historical interest; regarding Hood's campaign in Georgia and Tennessee; the responsibility for Confederate disasters, which he places on General Beauregard; etc. He refers to Beauregard as an "artful dodger."
    - A.L.S., 6pp. 8vo., January 14, 1880. (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Regarding Beauregard's actions in the Tennessee campaign.
    - A.L.S. 4pp. 8vo., November 6, 1884. (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Referring to Beauregard's published articles, his incapacity, and misrepresentations.
  - General Johnson Hagood, A.L.S., 2pp. 4to, June 22, 1881, to General Beauregard. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Written as governor of South Carolina. Inviting Beauregard to be a guest of the State and criticizing strongly Davis' account of the battle of Drury's Bluff.
  - General Beauregard, A.L.S., 2pp. 4to, July 2, 1881. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    This is a draft of a letter to General Hagood, replying to the previous letter. Strongly criticizing Davis and his book.
  - General Jubal Early, A.L.S., 20pp. 4to, August 22, 1881, to General Beauregard (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Reviewing Davis' Rise and Fall of the Confederacy and upholding him against General Beauregard's attack. Discusses at length the Battles of Bull Run, Shiloh, Petersburg, etc.
  - General Beauregard
    - A.L.S., 3pp. 4to, September 15, 1881, to General Early, replying to the preceding letter. (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Saying that a further discussion of Davis' book would be useless, as his own views and Early's are so widely divergent. This is a draft of the letter to Early kept by Beauregard.
    - A.L., written in pencil, 6pp., folio, September, 1881, to General Early. (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Referencing discussion of his letter criticizing Davis' Rise and Fall of the Confederacy.
  - Joseph E. Johnston, A.L.S., 4pp. 8vo. March 21, 1874, to General Beauregard. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Containing reference to General Lee and the contemplated removal of General Johnston from command.
  - General Thomas Jordan
    - A.L.S., 2pp. 4to, February 6, 1869, to General Beauregard. (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Criticizing Davis' "wicked policies," suggesting that Johnston and General Beauregard should join to expose these policies.
    - A.L.S., 9pp. 8vo, with a second A.L.S. of General Jordan, 9pp. 8vo. (Box 2, Folder 8)
      The two letters are dated March 1 and March 17, 1871. They both refer to Alfrend's Life of General Davis, which he states to be "full of historical errors and teeming with lies."
  - General W.S. Walker, A.L.S., 3pp. 4to, June 27, 1881, to General Beauregard. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Referring to Davis' Rise and Fall of the Confederacy and his unjust prejudice against Beauregard.
  - General M.J. Wright, A.L.S. 1p. 4to, June 24, 1881, to General Beauregard. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Concurring in Beauregard's estimate of Davis' book. Saying that it is full of errors and omissions.
  - Augustas J. Evans
    - A.L.S., 6pp. 4to, January 14, 1863. To General Beauregard (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Regretting that Davis discarded Beauregard's plan of campaign. Speaks of insubordination in the army and Lincoln's "infamous proclamation." With pencil note on a small slip of paper signed with initials.
    - A.L.S., 8pp. 8vo, January 30, 1864. (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Denouncing Davis and the government at Richmond and attacking Lincoln.
  - General Jubal Early, A.L.S., 4pp. 4to, July 11, 1873, to General Beauregard. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Giving his views of the unification movement in Louisiana, which he argues against.
- GENERAL W.T. SHERMAN AND HIS CRITICS
  ALL bound in full levant
  - General W.T. Sherman, A.L.S., 3pp., 4to, November 22, 1865. Written to B.F. Wade, Chairman of the Committee on the Conduct of the War. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Referring to material he has regarding the events during the various campaigns in which Sherman took part.
  - General Braxton Bragg, A.L.S., 4pp., 4to, February 9, 1866. To General Beauregard (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Giving at length his reminiscences of General Sherman and conversations with him in New Orleans just before the war.
  - General Jubal A. Early
    - A.L.S., 4pp. 8vo., March 7, 1876, to General Beauregard. (Box 2, Folder 9)
      A caustic criticism of General Sherman's book, just published.
    - A.L.S., 4pp. 8vo., March 17, 1876, to General Beauregard. (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Further criticizing Sherman's memoirs.
  - General Thomas Jordan, A.M. Beauregard's Chief of Staff, 12pp. 4to. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Rough draft of General Jordan's review of Sherman's memoirs, addressed to the editor of the New York Herald.
- ANDREW JACKSON AND JOHN RANDOLPH
  Bound together in half morocco.
  - Mrs. Martha Randolph, A.L.S., 4pp. 4to, Monticello, May 13, 1815. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Mrs. Randolph was Thomas Jefferson's daughter. The Letter refers to John Randolph's accusations against the wife of Gouveneur Morris. He accuses Mrs. Morris of murder, licentiousness, and of being the mother of an illegitimate child.
  - John Randolph, A.L.S., March 15, 1817, 4pp. 4to. (Box 2)
    Containing some interesting autobiographical information.
  - Francis Scott Key, A.L.S., 2pp. 4to, May 6, 1833. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    With Henry Ashton, A.L.S., 3pp. 4to, May 6, 1833; Henry Ashton, A.L.S., 2pp. 4to, May 13, 1833; all to Hon. A.B. Taney, Attorney General. With A.L. in third person from Taney to the President, May 16, 1833. These letters are in reference to insult offered to President Jackson by Lieutenant Randolph, who tweaked the President's nose. The letters contain a full account of what happened on this occasion and the attempts to arrest Randolph. The incident is referred to on pp. 715-716 and 728 in Bassett's Life of Andrew Jackson.
  - Andrew Jackson, A.L.S., 2pp. 4to, 1807 ca. January 13, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Demanding an apology for a statement that Jackson was engaged in the treason of Colonel Burr. The letter is addressed to James Sanders and is apparently the first draft.
  - Rachael Jackson, A.L.S., 3pp. 4to, Hermitage, July 18, 182-. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    An interesting letter by the wife of the president; the spelling is remarkable. It refers to the attacks made upon her on account of the irregularity of her marriage to Jackson.
  - Henry Clay
    - A.L.S. 1p. 4to, August 4, 1827. (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Referring to the possibility of Clay's being challenged to a duel by Jackson and saying that he will be "prepared for any and every honorable event." With addressed envelope.
    - A.L., in the third person, 1p. 4to, June 9, 1834. (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Stating that he has never "had of any Jackson functionary the slightest favor."
  - William Reed, A.L.S., 4pp. 4to, January 13, 1815. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Referring to the Battle of New Orleans, to John Randolph, etc.
  - W.B. Lewis, A.L.S., Fairfield, November 7, 1845, 3pp. 8 vo., to John C. Calhoun. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Suggesting that Calhoun should visit Jackson at the Hermitage.
  - Two letters in the hand of Winfield Scott. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    The first letter is a copy of a letter from him to Jackson, dated December 11, 1823. The second is a copy of Jackson's reply, bearing the same date. On the back of the first letter is a note in Scott's hand, explaining the incident that caused this correspondence. The note reads, "It has been long rumored, probably without foundation, but it was nevertheless believed by many, that General Jackson had threatened to assault or challenge me the first time we should happen to approach each other. Hence for six days I frequented the capitol and other public places where General Jackson was to be found in Washington and then addressed him this letter." The letter notified Jackson that Scott would remain in Washington for six days. In the reply Jackson says that if Scott wises to approach him on friendly terms, he will be met with a corresponding feeling on Jackson's part.
  - Andrew Jackson, A.L.S., 2¼pp., folio, January 8, 1813. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Written to his wife Rachael in a very flamboyant style. Referring to his country's call, the necessity of their separation, etc. [Folded and Cracking]
  - Martin Van Buren, A.L.S., 3pp. 4to. April 8, 1826. (Box 2, Folder 10)
    Re: duel between Clay and Randolph.